Finding Aid for W. B. Pillsbury pamphlets and reprints, 1900-1950
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
W. B. Pillsbury pamphlets and reprints 1900-1950
Pillsbury, W. B. (Walter Bowers), 1872-1960.
42 items (1 box)
[726] DA 2; P642; P186
Pillsbury was professor of psychology at the University of Michigan from 1897 to 1942; collection consists of reprints of articles an book reviews.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was assembled forma variety of sources.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Walter Bowers Pillsbury was professor of psychology at the University of Michigan, teaching first in the philosophy department and then helping to establish a psychology department. Pillsbury was born July 21, 1872 in Burlington, Iowa. He studied at Penn College, the University of Nebraska, and Cornell University where he received his Ph. D. degree in 1896. After teaching for a year at Cornell, Pillsbury in 1897 came to the University of Michigan as an instructor in psychology (in the philosophy department). In 1901, he became director of the psychology laboratory. In 1910, he was made full professor and in 1929, when the department of psychology was established, he was appointed chairman.
Before coming to the university, there were only occasional lectures in psychology, given by philosophy professors. Pillsbury introduced regular courses in psychology. He also established the psychological laboratory which introduced students to laboratory work and stimulated extensive experimentation with humans as well as animals. In his research and writing, Pillsbury was renowned for his work in the area of reasoning and attention, publishing monographs on both topics. He was skilled as a teacher and lecturer, and was a prolific writer. Pillsbury retired from the university in 1942 and died in 1960.
The Walter Pillsbury pamphlets and reprints collection consists of articles and book review on various topics in psychology, including articles about contemporary psychologists Edouard Claparede, Harvey A. Carr, James McKeen Cattell, John Dewey, Joseph Jastrow, and Clarence Stone Yoakum
Subjects:
Carr, Harvey, 1873-; Claparède, Edouard, 1873-1940.; Cattell, James McKeen, 1860-1944.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Jastrow, Joseph, 1863-1944.; Washburn, Margaret Floy, 1871-1939.; Yoakum, Clarence Stone, 1879-1945; Psychology.
- Pamphlets and Reprints.
  - An attempt to harmonize the current psychological theories of the judgment. 1907 (Box 1)
  - Attention. undated
  - Attention: a reply. 1909
  - Attention waves as a means of measuring fatigue. 1903
  - Body form and introversion-extroversion. 1939
  - A case of mental conflict. 1936
  - Clarence Stone Yoakum. 1879-1945.
  - The common points in recent theories of problem solving. 1939
  - The concept in psychology. undated
  - Correlations between the university-grades of parents and children and of siblings. 1939
  - Does the sensation of movement originate in the joint? 1901
  - Edouard Claparede. 1873-1940.
  - The ego and empirical psychology. 1907
  - An extension of the Kohler-Restorff inhibition phenomenon. 1943.
    (with H.L. Raush)
  - Gestalt vs. concept as a principle of explanation in psychology. 1926
  - Harvey A. Carr: 1873-1954. 1955
  - James McKeen Cattell 1860-1944. 1947
  - John Dewey 1859-1952. 1957
  - Joseph Jastrow 1863-1944. 1944
  - Knowledge in modern psychology. 1950
  - Margaret Floy Washburn (1871-1939). 1940
  - The new developments in psychology in the past quarter century. 1917
  - A new form of piston recorder and some of the changes of the volume of the finger which it records. 1899
  - A note on 'advancing and retreating' colors. 1937
  - The place of movement in consciousness. 1911
  - Propaganda and the democratic state. 1943
  - The psychological nature of casualty. 1904
  - The psychology of Edward Bradford Titchener. 1928
  - Recent naturalistic theories of reasoning. 1924
  - Retroactive and proactive inhibition in immediate memory. 1940
  - The role of the type in simple mental processes. 1911
  - Secondary rhythms of the normal human heart. 1899
  - Selection--an unnoticed function of education. 1921
  - A study in apperception. 1897
  - A suggestion toward reinterpretation of Introspection. 1904
  - Suggestions for a compromise of existing controversies in psychology. 1922
  - Titchener and James. 1943
  - Trial and error as a factor in evolution. 1906
  - The units of experience--meaning or gestalt. 1933
  - What is native in the so-called instincts? 1927
  - Book Reviews
  - "How We Learn" by Boyd H. Bode (book review) from American Journal of Psychology, 1941
  - "Psychologie der Veranderungsauffassung" by Von L. Wilhelm Stern (book review) from The Critical Review, 1900
Related Material
W. B. Pillsbury papers, 1890-1942 (3.5 linear feet) are held by the Bentley Historical Library. Walter